Back to slides for a while.
As a brief recap, both from last week and
actually also from the preceding video today,
let me recall a few notions/observations.
Before we will then, again, see this both
for the CodeWorld library, specifically,
and then also for some more practical
examples; to play around with, and also
more expressivity in terms of new syntax
features that we haven't seen yet.
So, what we discussed previously was
expressions, as opposed to commands:
expressions as syntactic structures.
And I gave you, as a way to remember this or to
distinguish what are expressions in languages that
you know, for example: it would be the things that
could occur after "=" in a variable assignment.
As things that evaluate to something,
then can be assigned to a variable.
So, that would be the things that you would
call an expression, also in other languages.
And the point was that in Haskell, for
example, basically everything is an expression.
Programming there consists, almost
exclusively, of expression writing.
What are values?
Values are the results of
evaluating an expression.
So, they are obtained by combining
values of subexpressions.
There also was this idea that
evaluation order should not be relevant.
If you have an expression which is combined out
of subexpressions in such an expression-style way,
values can actually be replaced by expressions
and expressions can be replaced by their values.
In a language where all that matters
is expressions and their values.
Opposed to that are commands, syntactic structures
that are not so much characterized by what,
if anything at all, they evaluate to,
but rather by what effect they have.
So, things like assignment statements
that would change storage cells,
or keywords/commands for looping, or things
that are not about evaluating some expression,
but about doing something
or about having an effect.
And that's a different kind of
structure in a programming language.
And it's still a more dominant structure
in imperative programming languages,
because they are about doing something
rather than about calculating values.
And there was this important observation already
alluded to above, that if you are in a pure
setting (so you don't have commands, and also the
expressions that we have are pure expressions),
then any pure expressions that have the
same value can be replaced by each other,
without changing the behaviour of the program.
That's what I did when I calculated
with programs in the previous video.
And that's also what, for example, a
compiler can use for optimizing a program.
More specifically for the CodeWorld sublanguage:
there now, our expressions are about pictures.
So, the values of expressions are pictures or
ingredients needed for Pictures,
like colours, coordinates, etc.
They can be named, etc.
You have done this already in
the first exercise, of course.
And for this, you have used functions/operators.
Here I list some along with their types.
You were not forced to use types in the first
exercise tasks, but if you have looked at the
documentation, you would
have found something like:
The 'circle' function takes a radius, which
is a real number, and gives a picture.
There are other notations,
that are not exactly like that in Haskell, but we
have them on this slide, in order to be similar to
functions and their types, the way you are
used to from mathematics, from set theory.
So, for example, the "polygon"
function is also about returning a picture, but
it actually takes a list of coordinate pairs.
Of course, a pair of coordinates is what would, in
mathematics, be presented by a Cartesian product.
So, taking R x R in order to
get pairs of real numbers.
And a list of such things will be an argument
of the 'polygon' function to get a picture.
For "colored", you take two arguments, a
colour and a picture, and return a picture.
We talked about this before.
And likewise, for more than two arguments,
you get something like a three-way
Cartesian/cross product of two times a
real number (for x- and y-directions)
for a movement, and then some
picture that you want to move.
And the result is a picture,
namely, the moved picture.
Actually, concerning the types: You may
have seen this already, for example,
in error messages in CodeWorld - if your program
didn't work, and there was an error message,
then you might have seen the types of these
functions, and they looked a bit different.
I will come back to this later.
That actually, for syntactical reasons, or reasons
about organization of function application
in Haskell, you will rarely see this cross.
You will see some other syntactic means
of expressing, for example, a binary
function or a function with three arguments, etc.
But mathematically, in
spirit, this is what we have.
For example, a combination: the and-symbol (&)
here takes two pictures and returns one picture.
I already talked in the previous video about
properties/laws that we can think about.
They are like arithmetic laws in mathematics.
But they now talk about the
functions that we have in our domain.
In this case, I talked
about rotation and colouring.
But I also started writing down the
law for translation and colouring,
and this would be the complete version of that.
And the list of functions that we consider grows.
So, there will be more things
that we can do with pictures.
Then you could always also think about new laws.
You don't have to prove them, of course.
In this lecture, the point is: If you
are aware of reasonable properties/laws
about the functions that you're working
with, then you can write nicer programs.
And you can refactor your
programs with much more confidence
than by just guessing what
you should do or not do.
Now, inside the CodeWorld library we can make the
next step and move from pictures to animations.
That's a very small step, actually,
because an animation, as I already
indicated before on an intuitive level,
is just a picture that changes with time.
And mathematically, such a dependence on time
would simply be by introducing parameters.
This is an example you see here, which
is a small variation of the example from
last week, where we basically had
no animation here, just a drawing.
We didn't have this t parameter in the
recent example that I walked through
in the expression-style discussion in CodeWorld.
In one of them, there was a fixed value here.
So, there was a colored red triangle
which was moved to somewhere.
And now, by saying "well, actually, let
me make this dependent on the time t",
this is already an animation.
I simply have to change the call above, here, to
also express that now I want to have an animation.
And I am making this happen by
the function here, and also,
instead of defining a scene as a Picture,
I define a function from Double to Picture.
So, this is something like the R from the previous
slides, the mathematical R, the real numbers.
So, the function depends on time, so
its first variable is the parameter t,
in the straightforward mathematical
interpretation and style.
This parameter is never set by us here.
So, you never see me, in this short piece of
code, setting the t to some specific value.
We can do this and play
around with the example code.
We can also consider specific calls of
the 'scene' function with the values 1, 2,
3, whatever, with specific values.
But for an animation this is not
something that I, as a programmer, do.
Another observation is: There is no
for-loop or other explicit control.
If you were considering a moving
triangle in another language,
you might consider that you write a for-loop,
which actually takes a variable t for time,
and then steps through different time steps:
t = 1, 2, 3, 4, whatever, in a for-loop; and
then use this to make repeated calls to a drawing
function to simulate or animate a moving triangle.
That's not what's happening here,
because we're more concerned about
expressing this mathematically.
And mathematically, this expression
is the perfect way of describing what
it means that the position of
the triangle depends on the time.
So, there is no explicit control.
Instead, somehow, this
animationOf-construct takes care of this.
And as a user of the library, we
don't need to know how it does that.
It does that by making clever decisions
about how often to call the 'scene' function,
maybe in sync with the browser's refresh rate,
decides when and with which values it should
call the 'scene' function, and then combines all
the pictures that result into a nice animation
(that can be shown in the browser, in the
case that you will use CodeWorld online, or
in other ways if you use it offline).
The point is, the animationOf-construct does this.
It is a function which takes another function,
in this case a 'scene' function, as an argument.
It is not something that we
have implemented ourselves.
It's a part of the library, or semantics
of what an animation is in CodeWorld.
And we can simply use it, and
will make more and more use of it.
Also you, in the next exercise tasks.
The use of functions to describe dynamic behaviours
shouldn't come as a surprise to
you (or most of you), I think.
Much of engineering outside
computer science works that way.
And at least from your high-school physics, you
also have seen many examples in mechanics, where a
lot of behaviours or situations in
experiments are described that way.
So, let's look at this case
of, basically, throwing a ball.
I think in physics schoolbooks,
this would be called "parabolic throwing".
Where we throw something at a start angle.
And if you looked up in such physics textbooks
how the experiment can be described, then you
would find something like these formulas here:
describing the x- and y-positions based
on the parameter t (the current time).
And there is some starting
velocity in the x-direction and some
starting velocity in the y-direction.
And then since in the x-direction
it is a uniform movement, it's
basically this multiplication of
this factor and the current time.
And in the y-direction, because there's also
gravity, which basically leads to this curve
that results here, we also have
to have this other component.
This is the mathematics of what
throwing a ball in this fashion means.
And that is a complete description
of the dynamics of the system.
And it also serves as the
implementation if you like.
So, in CodeWorld, you could
write a small program which
basically animates this movement of this ball.
And what you write down is
really what we see above
from the mathematics side, except that
you have to write it in Haskell style.
You will recognize these expressions down here for
the x- and y-values, of course, in program syntax.
Not, for example, this fraction syntax here.
But apart from that, and
setting some specific parameters
and specific constants, that's really
the implementation of what we see above.
Very closely matched with the
mathematics/physics side to programming.
Also, this is not something
that's super surprising.
But it is also interesting, because
it will be useful for illustrating,
by playing with this program,
the use of specific concepts.
For example, scope.
One difference that you
might already observe here,
is for example that the x and y up here are
explicit functions that take this t parameter.
Whereas down here, where I compute x
and y, because I want to use them for
describing the position of my small ball (which is
this "circle 0.1"), they are not functions of t.
Why don't they have to be functions of t?
Because they are local definitions.
So, we describe the 'scene' function.
The function takes an argument t.
Then there on the right-hand
side, the t is in scope.
It can be used.
And if I introduce a local definition here
for x (or even several ones for x and for y),
then the t is in scope, but I don't have to, like
above here, explicitly pass the t as an argument.
This is something that you can play around with.
So, what happens if you move
these x and y to the top level?
I talked about organization of programs before.
Having local definitions or top-level/global
definitions is something that we can observe here.
Also, this is a program largely without keywords.
Because we are in expression-style.
Just as the mathematical world doesn't know
keywords, only knows mathematical symbols,
variables, operators and combinations
of expressions; the same applies here.
So, there are no keywords.
The "where" could be
considered a keyword, probably,
but it's really just something
for organizing our expression.
It's not like the "while" or
"for" loop keywords in an imperative language,
that it really drives the whole computation.
So, this "where" here is a keyword, but it's
really just a helper for organizing
our mathematical expressions.
What's really important about this
program is the expressions that we build.
Speaking of expressions, which
I seem to do all the time,
we will, of course, need a few more ingredients
than just operators, constants, and variables.
So, I gave this idealized idea, that
there are only mathematical functions,
mathematical symbols, variables, and
constants, to build larger programs.
There will be something more needed,
but it will still be expression-style.
So, the "where" keyword from the
previous slide was already an example,
where something was introduced that is not just a
value, or something that is itself an expression.
So, it's a keyword for organizing expressions.
And actually, there will be
further syntactic constructs
that allow us to build more interesting,
larger, and more useful expressions.
And I call this "rich expressions".
I will introduce these features
one by one in the following
material, and in each case motivated
by some example in CodeWorld.
Let us discuss this case.
Let's assume that, differently from the example
we saw today (where we had continuous distribution
throughout time, so our function was dependent
on time to express continuous distribution
of pictures through time, namely as animations),
we instead want to have a discrete distribution,
in some sense, throughout space.
So, we don't want to have a moving triangle,
but maybe we want to have many triangles
which are static, but are separated in space.
So, they appear at different places
on our coordinates plane, for example.
Now, of course, the magic
of the 'animationOf' function provided
before is not applicable anymore.
Because there is no obvious way how to distribute
things throughout space,
unlike time moving forwards.
So for every point we simply have
to say where our triangle is.
Now, we maybe want to have a
certain pattern on the screen,
how these different triangles
should statically be placed.
And that's not something that somehow can come
from something like the 'animationOf' function.
So, now it is something that
the programmer would have to do.
And of course, the programmer could do that.
The programmer could take our old 'scene' function,
which given the parameter places the triangle at
some point, and previously used this parameter
in the 'animationOf' function to express movement.
Now we could simply say: Let's instead make
individual calls to the 'scene' function
with different values for this parameter.
Then, certainly, we can express the
places that are of interest to us.
But then we would have to replicate these calls.
We would have to write down
"scene of 1", "scene of 1.5",
if that's the two copies that we want
to have of our "scene", of our triangle.
And if you want to have ten copies of
the triangle, then you would have to ask
ten calls to this 'scene' function
which draws one triangle.
But that is not something you want
to do by hand, probably, right?
It is also not something that you
want to write down in the program:
ten times the same code, just
with different arguments.
What to do instead?
Let's think about imperative programming.
What would we do?
That would probably take a for-loop.
We would say we want ten copies
of our call of the 'scene' function.
Then let's write a for-loop in which we use
the loop variable in such a way that we get
our ten copies of the triangle, for example.
But we don't have that, right?
That's something that I said from the
start, that we don't think in terms of
such control constructs, where we express
what to do, or express a repeated effect.
That wouldn't be expression-style.
It is not something that is available
in that way in a functional language.
We don't have this.
Well, then probably we should have something else.
We want to be able to express this, of course.
So, what do we have instead?
What we have, are the so-called
"list comprehensions", which
are our first kind of "rich
expressions" to consider.
And you see an example here.
You may also already have seen such
comprehensions in other programming languages,
but they originated in functional programming.
So, what do we have here?
We have our old 'scene' function in a sense.
So, it's the same thing.
I just rename the parameter from t to d,
because now it is not anymore about time,
but maybe about distance (so, where
I want to place my triangles).
So, this is unchanged from before, because
I still want to call this function.
But then I use it differently.
Rather than passing it to an animationOf-call,
I instead pass it to a drawingOf-call,
but actually I pass several copies.
And I do this in a list.
So, the square brackets here are for list syntax.
And in particular, I combined two things
here: I have some function 'pictures'.
It's given down here with its type.
So, what does it say?
It gives a picture and it
takes a list of pictures.
You might think it is a set of
pictures, but it is actually a list.
So, several pictures are turned into one picture.
You could think of the 'pictures' function
as a version of the &-operator, but now it
can work on arbitrarily many pictures at once.
Whereas the &-operator was a binary operator,
which basically combines two pictures.
Here we have several pictures
that we combine into one.
And what are our pictures that
we want to combine into one?
They are this expression here, which is
repeated here, a "list comprehension".
Because it comprehensively describes several
elements of the list at a time.
And how does it do that?
Well, it contains calls of the 'scene' function
for some values.
And these values are drawn from some other
list.
What it is saying, in a sense, precisely is:
Let the d variable be taken from 0, 1, 2,
3, 4, 5, so six calls (basically six copies);
and for each of these values, call the 'scene' function,
which will give one version of this moved
triangle; put them all into a list; pass that
list of six pictures to the 'pictures' function,
which will turn them into one picture.
And that's the picture that we draw.
So, from this piece of code you should expect
six triangles at different places throughout
the space of our coordinate system.
So, in some sense, of course this reminds
us of a for-loop.
You could say this is a for-loop, but it really
isn't.
And that's important for several reasons.
This is not a for-loop.
For example, there really is not "one after
another".
So, it is not like: first, draw this; then,
draw this; somehow put them into an order.
What comes out here is a list of values, and
these are completely independent.
None of them is computed before or after the
other, mathematically.
Of course, on our sequential computer, they
will be evaluated in some order, but this
is completely irrelevant for the values.
Mathematically, it is just a list of, in this
case, six values.
And there is not a before- or after-notion,
which is, of course, the crucial notion for
a for-loop.
For a for-loop, you want to know whether it
will work backwards or forwards.
So, does it count up or down?
These all are things that are important for
a for-loop or any kind of loop in an imperative
language, but not for list comprehensions.
So, these are independent computations.
There is also no effect, where somehow one
iteration influences the next one.
So, the scene-call for the value, let's say
d = 1, cannot have any effect on the "scene"-call
for the value d = 4, no matter whether 4 occurs
after or before 1 in this list.
So, these are independent computations, whereas
in a for-loop, of course, you do expect (for
example, via global variables or local variables
that you assign values to) that the order
in which things happen in the loop is important,
and that the second run through the loop body
could really have an impact on what happens
in the fifth or sixth or whatever iteration.
That's not something that happens here, because
this is really like a mathematical set comprehension.
This notation that you know from mathematics:
Let me take the set of all "2 * n", where
n comes from the natural numbers.
This is what you should think of when you
think about a list comprehension.
It is also very close in syntax, and that's
by design.
So, you could think of this as the "element
symbol".
So, d is an element of this list.
And for each such element, I compute whatever
is written here.
Then I get different pictures.
I put them into a list, just as here they
are put into a set.
And that list, like here this set, is then
what I pass on.
In this case, it is what is passed to the 'pictures' function,
in order to combine my different pictures
into one big one, which is then drawn.
This is the way to think about a list comprehension,
not like a for-loop (where one thing happens
after another).
To further explain list comprehensions: a
few artificial examples.
Not about pictures, just numbers, pairs of
numbers, etc.
Though, to start: something already shown
on the previous slide was a notation for simply
having a list of values.
There was this "0..5".
It was "all the numbers from 0 to 5".
Actually, this also comes in richer forms.
For example, one could get odd numbers by
starting with 1,3.. and then an upper bound.
Then it would give all the odd numbers up
to that number.
So, in this case, where the last number is
10 (which is not an odd number), it would
stop at 9.
And this could be used as one of the lists,
for example, that you put into a list comprehension
(to draw values like d on the previous slide).
Generally, these list comprehensions can have
this form.
Here we can see the parts that make up a list
comprehension.
In general, we have:
The body, that's the thing that you want to
compute for any combination of values drawn
from the later parts.
So, that's what ends up in the final set.
Usually, this will contain some variable or
variables, which are bound in this later part
of the list comprehension.
And here we have generators.
Something like "x from this 1..10" would be
a generator, because it generates new elements
for which you compute the body.
And then, there also can be guards.
Some predicate, some condition.
Basically, a Boolean value.
You have not seen this yet, but there is a
function 'even' in Haskell, which takes a number
and gives "true" if that number is even;
otherwise it gives "false".
So, what we are saying here is: For each x
from 1 to 10, check whether that number is
even.
That will be true for 2, 4, 6, 8, 10.
And then for any number drawn from this generator
which also passes this guard expression, the
body will be computed.
And the results will be accumulated in the
list.
So, this will be square numbers of all the
even numbers between 1 and 10.
So: 2^2, 4^2, 6^2, 8^2, and 10^2.
It gives these results.
Some other syntactic possibility is that inside
this list of things, like generators and guards,
we can also define local variables.
So let's say that we want to do something
that results in the same list, but in a different
way.
What we do here is:
Let x be anything from 1 to 10 (so this will
choose 1 to 10, one after the other, for x).
Then, for each such x, we compute some auxiliary
value.
So, we compute y from the x that we have drawn
here, and then we give the guard expression
on the y.
So, what this is doing is that it takes all
the numbers from 1 to 10, computes the squares,
and checks whether the squares are divisible
by 4.
Which, of course, ends up with the same result
as here.
Because this will be exactly the squares of
even numbers, because of course, the square
is dividable by 4 exactly if the original
number is even.
But it just happens in this case.
The point is that we can define local values
in between, and use them.
Another thing to notice in this example is
this "==".
This is the equality operator.
And it is really different from this.
So, this is defining y to be x^2, and this
"==" is the operator which checks whether
this call computing the modulo of y at division
by 4 is equal to the value 0.
Then we can have cases where we not only have
several guards, but also have several generators.
This happens here.
Instead of having just one variable, like
here, or one generator variable and one computed
auxiliary variable, we can actually have two
variables which are drawn from generators.
So, here we are saying: Let's take x from [1,
2, 3] and also y from [1, 2, 3] and then compute
something like the product of x and y.
And then what we get are all the products
of a value from [1, 2, 3] and another value
from [1, 2, 3].
So, this 1 will be from multiplying 1 * 1,
and then we get all the other combinations
as well.
Once you have more than one variable in the
body of a list comprehension, the question
becomes: In which order are the things combined
into a result list?
In the previous example with the multiplication,
that was not obvious from the result, because
we can't see which factors were combined.
But, for example, if you consider this example:
The x comes from [1, 2, 3] and y from [4,
5], and we build the pair of the values x
and y (maybe as coordinates); then we see
in the result how things are arranged.
You see that first the x from [1, 2, 3] is
picked as 1, and then this is combined with
each possible choice for the y from [4, 5].
So, we have (1,4) and (1,5).
And then we get all combinations where x has
chosen the second element of its generator
and this is combined with y being 4 and 5
in these two elements, and so on.
So, we get this list of results.
This is, of course, the Cartesian product
of these two lists considered as sets.
And the order in which it is output is by
first making a choice for x, and then all
possible choices for y, and then taking the
next choice for x, etc.
This also means that if you change the order
of such generators, you get the same values,
but possibly in a different order.
So, take the same body, but switch the order
of these generators; then the resulting list
has a slightly different order.
Because now first the y is chosen, and then
for each valid choice for y, for example for
the choice "y is 4", we consider all choices
for the x.
So, we get (1,4), (2,4), (3,4).
And if there was another variable here, like
z, then that should be either known from the
context, or somehow from the part of the program
in which this expression occurs, or the z
should be set by another generator here.
So, we can't have variables that are not known
at all, either from the context or from this
list of generators.
This can also become more interesting.
The generators themselves can depend on each
other.
Or more precisely, a later generator list
can depend on something which is occurring
earlier in the list of generators/guards.
So, what this is saying, is: I want to have
all the pairs x and y where x comes from [1,
2, 3] and y comes from [1 .. x] (1 to x).
So for the choice "x is 1", then for y we
also have the choice "1", because [1 .. 1]
(1 to 1) is just [1].
So, we only get (1,1).
But for the choice "x is 2" we get that y
is chosen from 1 to 2.
So, we get (2,1) and (2,2).
And for "3", we get (3,1), (3,2), (3,3), because
for a different x we have different choices,
because we have different lists in this place.
It wouldn't work the other way around.
We couldn't mention y here, if y occurs as
a later generator variable.
Of course, you could use y at this place,
because y is the first generator variable
here.
And this can become interesting also in different
ways.
For example, you could also decide to actually
pick x and y at once.
For this, we actually have to have a list
of pairs here.
So, you also see here: It doesn't just work
for numbers (actually, we have seen it before
in the context of pictures), but it also works
for other data types in Haskell.
So, let's say we take strings.
If you have a list of pairs of strings, then
we could also have a generator expression
which says "let me pick all the (x,y) pairs
from this list".
And then, of course, we wouldn't get a Cartesian
product as above (where every choice for
this is combined with every choice for that).
Now here, what we say, is: The first choices
x and y are this and this.
And then we collect their concatenation.
That's what this symbol does.
So, we concatenate "a" and "b", which gives
the string "ab".
And the next choice is not somehow "a" with
"c".
Instead, the next choice is really: We apply
this pair pattern and get its ingredients
from the next pair of the generator list.
So, the next choice would be: x is "c" and
y is "d".
So, the next thing to be computed here would
be the string "cd", and that's it.
No crosswise comparison, because here we bind
x and y.
We choose x and y at once from all these pairs.
Whereas here, we had independent choices for
the x and for the y.
That's why we get more results up here.
Here, we use this matching against the pair.
That's also something that often would be
written down in mathematical set notation.
Taking a step back again, let's ask where
we are now, concerning expressiveness.
Some take home messages from the examples we have seen:
We can now via a function express non-constant
behaviour.
So, functions in the mathematical sense.
No weird keywords for imperative behaviour,
no loops, just pure expressions.
Such a description, like for our animations,
defines behaviour as a whole.
So, not in a piecemeal fashion.
That is not really a concept of "run this
piece of animation, then that piece, and then
something else".
That was not something that happens in such
a description of an animation in terms of
mathematical functions.
Indeed, there is not even a concept of "this
piece of animation stops at some point".
We didn't say "use this from 0 to 10 seconds"
or something like that.
We said: f(t) is something, namely an expression
which describes a picture, in which a t might
occur.
And that then is an ever-running animation.
It does this for increasing t however long
this may be.
There is no end point.
Of course, this doesn't mean that we don't
want to express possibly non-continuous behaviour.
You might want to run an animation just for
some time, or switch from some function to
another function (from some animation to another
animation), based on some condition about
time (for example, time intervals).
But we are not going to do this by resorting
to sequential commands.
We are not going to use imperative keywords,
or semicolons for composition in a sequential
way.
Like saying: "this animation and then that
animation".
That would be too big a deviation from the
mathematical idea of expressing functions.
So, we need something else.
Unfortunately, list comprehensions are not
the answer either.
We just introduced them in the last examples
for avoiding duplication of expressions.
For example, for expressing this discrete
distribution.
But it's not something that is used to define
functions.
List comprehensions define values.
They are list values, but they are values.
So, they are not defining, for example, an
animation which consists of several pieces.
So, we need something else.
And actually, some keywords which are used
inside expressions.
What we need is some way to express conditionals.
And this is done, as in probably almost all
programming languages that you know, by "if-then"
or "if-then-else".
Actually here, by "if-then-else".
So let's look at an example.
The "if", "then", and "else" are, of course,
keywords.
But they are used inside expressions.
So let's consider these examples.
This example scene is, again, an animation;
because: from time to something.
And what does it say?
It makes a check on the time, whether it is
smaller than 3 or not.
And if so, then it computes this expression,
which depends on the t.
And if you look at it a bit, you will see
that it will basically animate a moving circle
which moves somehow diagonally (because x
and y will always have the same value, namely
the current time in seconds).
So, this will be a small circle that from the
origin moves in a diagonal fashion here.
But it does so only until t becomes 3.
Because when t is 3 plus something, then this
"if-then-else" will actually mean that the
"then" branch is not important and the "else"
branch will be the relevant one.
What do we have there?
What is "blank"?
This "blank" is a picture.
It's a predefined picture which shows nothing.
It's an empty picture.
Which you might consider to be a stupid picture
to have.
But actually here in this case, that is a
nice way to express that after three seconds
our animation shouldn't show anything anymore.
So, it will show the empty picture, namely
nothing.
Now, this notation here (this way of expressing
things) is similar to and reminds of conditionals
in mathematics.
These are keywords in Haskell, but they are
just ways of organizing an expression, actually
organizing several cases of expressions.
Mathematically, they are functions like f(x)
is: If x is more than zero (or some other
property), then this expression; otherwise
this expression.
And it will always evaluate to one of them.
It won't evaluate to both of them, nor to
one after the other.
It's a pure expression depending on the value
of x.
This is what we evaluate, or this.
And the same happens up here.
We can also compare the situation to other
languages you know, like C or Java.
There you also have an "if" construct and
an "if-else" construct.
So, this is the syntax for C or Java.
There are, or course, some syntactical differences
to what we've just seen.
But actually, the more important difference
is that we even have these two versions: just
an "if" or an "if-else".
Whereas in an expression language, the form
without the "else" does not make any sense.
So in Haskell we always have, and must have,
if-then-else.
Because we have a condition here, and either
this condition is true or false.
And even if it is false, we must have some
value.
That's different here.
Why is it different?
Because in C or Java we are writing commands,
and it's meaningful to say: there is no command.
You can say: If something holds, then do all
these commands, and otherwise don't do anything.
That's a reasonable thing to say in a command-based
language, where you have commands that execute.
Then you can say: Well, in some cases I don't
do anything.
That's fine.
But in a mathematical/expression-based language,
you must have some value.
Everything must evaluate to some value, and
you cannot say: under certain conditions,
I don't evaluate to anything.
You have to have some value.
So, you cannot have an "if-then" without the
"else" branch.
Because you have to compute a value.
Whereas here, you say you do some things,
and in some case you don't do anything.
That's fine.
That is some action.
It will be a no-action, but there is no value
required.
So actually, the "if-then-else" in Haskell
is not really so similar to "if-else", as
keywords, in C or Java.
It's actually more similar to this conditional
operator in those languages.
Which is also something that in C or Java
you use on the expression level; not with
commands (here, here, and here), but actually
with expressions.
This is something that could occur in an expression
on the right-hand side of a variable assignment,
whereas something like this cannot occur in
C or Java on the right-hand side of a variable
assignment.
Because it is about commands, and not about
expressions.
It is also a bit strange that you have two
ways of expressing conditionals in C and Java.
But that's because you have these two levels:
you have the commands and you have the expressions.
And in a language where you have only expressions
(where everything is expression-based), you
have only one of these forms.
This also means, for example, that in Haskell
(with all of this talk about syntactic compositionality
I already mentioned) you can name arbitrary
parts of these expressions.
You can name the expression as a whole.
You can put an "if-then-else" as an expression
inside a function call.
You can name parts of it.
Whereas for example here, you cannot name
this part of an "if".
That's the discussion I had in an earlier
video about expressions versus commands in
terms of naming subparts of a program.
Which is easily possible here, but not in
the command-based setting, which is where
the "if" and "if-else" of Java live in.
It's a bit different for this, because it's
expression-based.
But well, in Haskell everything is expression-based.
For the if-then-else in the earlier example,
we somehow intuitively want an "if-then" without
an "else".
Which we cannot have.
Then there must be some neutral value in an
algebraic sense.
So, there cannot be no value, but of course,
there are certain values that correspond to
"nothing".
Like in the picture case: the "blank" is something
like "no picture".
But it is a picture.
It's an empty picture.
It's a neutral value.
It's not "no value".
And the same is true for many types.
So let's say we have the same situation in
a list context.
We want to say: If a condition is true, then
we have some non-empty list, and otherwise
there isn't really anything.
But there isn't nothing; there is the empty
list.
So, we can use the empty list, because the
empty list is algebraically a neutral value
in the type of lists.
That is an observation that will probably
be useful for at least one of the next exercise
tasks.
And then there's another thing which I also
mentioned already on the previous slide, and
with which I want to finish this video now.
It is this remark that "if-then-else" is an
expression, so it can be part of a larger
expression.
You can name its parts, itself, etc.
So, what I want to emphasize here is really
this point of not hesitating, of really freely
using "if-then-else" as part of other expressions.
I have observed many times in the past that
students somehow are concerned or hesitant
to write something like this, where the "if-then-else"
is not somehow on the top-level (as you are
probably used to from other languages like
C or Java, where you can't really have this
inside some expression; you always have the
"if-then" as keywords on the outside, on the
top-level).
But there's no reason for this hesitation
in an expression-based language.
So, you can have something like this: f is
a function which takes three arguments, and
maybe x and y are the first two arguments,
and the last argument actually depends on
some condition.
You can write something like "if", "condition"
(expression), "then" some picture, some other
picture (or whatever is the type here).
The meaning of this is the same as below.
So, it is the same as if you would say: if
the condition is true, then you want to apply
f to x and y and this first expression, otherwise
you want to apply f to x and y and the last
expression.
So of course, you can write this and often
students at this stage do write this code
like this.
But actually, this code is expressing the
same, and it's actually nicer because it avoids
repetition.
It is more explicitly expressing that in any
case, you will apply f to x and y, and you
only still have to decide whether the last
argument is exp2 or exp3.
This is perfectly expressed in the first line,
and somewhat hidden (and takes more checking)
in the last line.
So in that sense, in situations like this,
I would prefer the first line, because it's
more clearly expressing what's going on.
But for this, you have to accept that "if-then-else"
is just an expression that can be used as
subexpression of whatever: other expressions,
functions, calls, etc.
Okay, I have to correct myself.
I actually didn't yet want to close the video.
I actually want to make a few more remarks
on syntax and types, and also syntax of types.
So, I actually announced this earlier in the
video that I have something to say on this,
also probably for your next exercise tasks.
Let's do this and then finish.
Earlier, I showed this and claimed that these
were the types of some of the primitives you
have seen and have been using
And I said that this is like mathematical
notation, like the Cartesian product.
For example, for a three-arguments-functions
like "translated", I said that there is this
Cartesian product of twice the real numbers,
and then the Picture type.
And I also said: This is not exactly what
you see if you look up the definitions of
these functions.
And indeed, what you instead will see is something
like that, also when you look into the online
documentation.
But this is really just, for certain reasons,
a different way of writing things down.
For example, if let's look at the "translated"
function.
It's a function with three arguments and whose
result is Picture.
Then how it's actually written as a type in
Haskell, is this notation, where even before
the first few arguments you also have this
arrow symbol.
So instead of having these three arguments
somehow denoted by having these two Cartesian
products here, and then the function arrow
to the result, actually the way it's written
is: first argument type, arrow, second argument
type, arrow, third argument type, and then
the result type.
Other than that, and of course switching from
this mathematical symbol for the real numbers
to the actual type "Double" in Haskell, that's
equivalent to up here.
And all the other types are also likewise
and similar.
Here, inside the list, there is also a different
thing.
So, you really want a list of pairs.
It is not a function like here, where you
say: turn this three-argument-function into
a notation like this, where we always have
the function arrow.
This would not make sense here, because this
is really a set of pairs.
And then the notation in Haskell simply is
not with the cross for the Cartesian product,
but actually also at type level you simply
write pairs.
So, this is the type of pairs of Doubles and
Doubles.
Then, in terms of syntax on the expression-
rather than type-level, I have already earlier
(in one of the example videos) commented at
some length on this difference between the
mathematical notation and the function notation.
So, this shouldn't be news to you at this point,
that we write in this form without that many
brackets or commas.
For nested function application, of course
we do need brackets sometimes.
For example, where an f call occurs as an
argument in the position of the g call, then
we can't avoid these brackets.
Because that wouldn't be clear, who calls
what.
But this is how we would then express that
this together is the second argument of this
g call.
We have also seen something like this already
in more complex expressions with "rotated"
and "colored" and whatever.
The same syntax as this one in particular,
where function application is with spaces
and without commas, is what is used at function
definition sites.
Again, you have seen this at least for "scene
t = something" (scene of t is something).
And it also applies if we have functions with
more than one argument.
So, something which in Java or C would look
like so: We declare that f is a function which
takes an integer and a character and returns
a float.
This would in Haskell turn into this more
mathematical way of writing down the types.
So, integer and character are the two argument
types, and float is the return type.
There are of course syntax differences like
that these types are written in uppercase.
But that of course is just how the language
works on the lexical level.
And then, naming the function: where here
the function is named in the type, and in
the definition it's named again.
We have f of "a" and "b" not in brackets and
commas, etc., but simply "f a b =" and then
we have the body of the function definition.
Of course, there are differences as well,
like that in the Java code here we would have
commands and we might not even have a return
from this call, because a function in Java
need not return something.
Well, here it would return a float, but you
could have "void", for example.
And then maybe the function doesn't return
anything.
So, it is not really a mathematical function.
In contrast, in Haskell, of course, there
has to be some expression here.
So, there must always come a float out of a
call of f on a and b (on some values, some
arguments).
And also there are differences like the semantics
of these local variables.
What they do is different in Haskell from
these imperative languages.
Here you could have assignments, where you
overwrite a and b.
Here a and b are inputs and they can be used
on the right-hand side, but they cannot be
changed.
So, the role of variables is different, which
you already know from previous examples, of
course.
Then there is an issue of whitespace and layout
in Haskell.
Haskell is a layout-sensitive language, which
means that if you group things like local
definitions, then the horizontal layout is
important.
The layout in the sense: in which column things
start.
What does this mean?
Let's consider "let" and "in".
This is another way to organize local definitions.
We already saw something like: "f x is something,
where ..." and then we had some local definitions.
Where the things that are locally defined
are mentioned after the main expression.
We can also have it the other way around,
but then we don't use "where" but rather "let-in".
So, what this is saying here is: We want to
compute the expression f c + f d, and inside
there we want to use some things, for example,
the y and the f.
Actually, y is used here, and f is a function
which will be used here.
So, it is not a top-level function which occurs
somewhere else in the program, but it's local
to this expression.
And then we say "let something and something
in" and then we use what we have defined before.
Differently than in the "where" case, where
we have mentioned the local definitions after
the expression in which they are used.
This is something that you can write down.
And it's important that these things start
in the same column here.
So in that sense, the layout (how far you
indent things) is important.
We could also avoid this and write explicit
grouping.
So, this is also valid in Haskell, where I
don't use layout.
I simply say: I want to group these two definitions,
and then we actually use semicolons and these
curly brackets.
And this is equivalent.
Then we don't have to be careful about the
layout, because these curly brackets and the
semicolon explain what the grouping is.
But if you don't use this, then you have to
be careful of the layout, as in other layout-sensitive
languages like Python (which came after).
This also means that, for example, these two
pieces of program are not accepted.
They would be rejected or not mean what you
think they mean, because the layout cannot
be used to group things.
Which also means that if you write Haskell
code, then you should prefer an editor in
which you can ensure that indenting via spaces
and via tabs is not mixed.
You should usually use spaces instead of tab
characters, because the compiler cannot, by
default, know what indentation level a tab
symbol corresponds to in your editor.
So, things might look okay to you when you
look in your editor, but actually what a compiler
sees is something like that.
So, that's a typical trap to fall into, if
you haven't programmed in a layout-sensitive
language before.
And now really finally for this video, let
me conclude by talking again about brackets,
basically, and writing expressions.
I mentioned already that we use fewer brackets
than you might expect if you haven't programmed
in a language with this kind of syntax rules
before.
So, for example, we don't need to bracket
the x argument in a call like this, because
this expression is just the same and is uniquely
parsable.
So, it's clear what this means.
We don't need extra brackets here.
And similarly, in calls like this, we don't
need brackets around these two function calls
whose results are added.
Because this function application (basically
this space here) binds tighter than all operators.
So, it is not necessary to say that you want
(f x) and then add this to (g y).
Actually, even if you write it like that,
the parser will consider this as one unit
which is added to this other expression.
So, this is one thing.
And we have already mentioned that Autotool
will also warn you about redundant brackets
and encourage you to remove them.
Then there is another thing that students
sometimes do if they have read Haskell example
code at other places or on the internet.
So, there is this possibility to save even
more brackets by using the dollar-operator.
Which would allow, for example, to avoid all
brackets in this expression by writing something
like that.
But I have to say I don't like the dollar-operator,
in particular in beginners' code, because
it gets easily misused, or used in a way that
doesn't really improve readability.
So actually, again, Autotool will discourage
or even forbid the use of the dollar-operator.
But I wanted to mention it at least, because
I know that some students read about it in
other places and then maybe are wondering
why they cannot use it in their exercise submissions.
That's basically because I am the dictator
here, and I prefer not to let you use this
too early, at least.
For more advanced Haskell programmers, this
can be an important function to use in structuring
their code, but not for you, I would say at
this point.
And as mentioned, sometimes Autotool gives
warnings about things like redundant brackets
or even overuse of this dollar-symbol.
And sometimes these are not just warnings,
but they are really enforced.
So, you will always have to read the feedback.
And if the feedback is red, then you know
that you really have to change something,
because you're not yet meeting the criteria.
Be it correctness, or be it style criteria
like the ones mentioned here and others later
on.